大家好 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
马斯克最近带我参观了SpaceX的猛禽发动机
I recently spent some time with Elon Musk and SpaceX's Raptor engines
我在一众猛禽2发动机中发现了一台较早版本
and I spotted one of their previous Raptors in a proverbial forest of Raptor 2 engines.
我觉得正好可以借此机会带大家了解
So I figured now would be a good time to go over some of the tweaks
SpaceX对这台有史以来最先进的火箭发动机的修改
that SpaceX has made to the most advanced rocket engine ever built.
因此本期视频我们将简单介绍猛禽发动机迄今为止所有的升级
So today we're gonna do a quick rundown on all the known changes we've seen with Raptor to date.
我们会介绍它的推力与性能
We'll go over their thrust and performance,
如何通过外观来了解其变化
how to spot the changes with their external designs,
并展望这款发动机未来将如何继续进化
and talk about how we expect to see this engine continue to evolve in the future.
我们开始吧!
Let's get started!
首先 相信大家都已经看到了 没错!
First things first let's address the elephant in the room. You're right.
我穿的不是T恤
I'm not wearing a T-shirt.
我穿的是一件印满了小猛禽发动机的衬衫
I'm actually wearing a dress shirt with little tiny Raptor engines all over it.
没错 这是我们期待已久的全新衬衫之一
That's right. This is one of our long awaited brand new dress wear shirts.
如果你喜欢航天 可能刚好又喜欢穿衣打扮
If you love aerospace and also love, or maybe need to dress up,
这些款式的衬衫绝对适合你
these are definitely the shirts for you.
请点击下方链接查看店里的新商品
Check these out and lots of other brand new stuff,
还有1:100的模型火箭哦
like our incredible 1:100 scale model rockets,
还有很多其他酷炫新品~
and lots of other really cool new stuff at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
回到本期视频
Okay, but for this video,
我们有相当多的讨论会围绕"全流量分级燃烧循环"
I need to mention that we're going to be talking a lot about the full flow stage combustion cycle
发动机压强 发动机冷却等术语
engine pressure and engine cooling techniques.
如果哪些词语对你来说很陌生
If any of this stuff is confusing to you,
av723951018
av300259217
请务必观看《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》
和《火箭发动机循环方式介绍》这两期视频
Be sure and watch my "Why don't rocket engines melt" video and my "Engine power cycles" video.
这两期视频一定会为你打好基础
I promise those will help set the stage
让大家能更好消化本期视频的内容
and arm you with all of the knowledge to make this video more digestible.
而本期视频也能让我对马斯克的采访更加容易理解
And this video is obviously meant to help make the interview more digestible too.
所以……都看看吧 希望大家能了解一切你们想知道的
So … watch 'em all and hopefully you'll know everything you need to know.
我们先大致了解一下猛禽发动机
Let's start off with an overview of Raptor.
猛禽发动机将为SpaceX即将推出的星舰和超重助推提供动力
Raptor will be powering SpaceX's upcoming Starship and Super Heavy booster.
目前 星舰上面级会有三台海平面猛禽发动机和三台真空猛禽发动机
Currently the Starship upper stage will have three sea level Raptors and three vacuum optimized Raptors,
可能在不久将来变为六台真空版本
but it'll likely go to six vacuum engines soon.
下面的超重助推将会安装33台左右的猛禽发动机
The Super Heavy booster on the other hand will be jam packed with 33ish Raptors,
我说"左右" 是因为不清楚他们之后会怎么改
give or take a few, 'cause you just never know what they're gonna do with the next ones,
星舰将因此成为推力最大的火箭
which will make it the most powerful rocket ever,
推力是送人类去月球的土星五号火箭推力的两倍多
with over twice as much thrust as the Saturn V rocket that took humans to the Moon.
猛禽发动机是一款以液氧和甲烷为燃料的液体火箭发动机
Raptor is a liquid fueled rocket engine running on methylox.
So, liquid methane and liquid oxygen.
两种推进剂的沸点都非常低
The boiling point of each of these propellants is very low,
液氧的沸点是-183°C 甲烷的沸点是-161°C
-183°C for oxygen and -161°C for methane,
因此 它们都是低温推进剂
which means they're cryogenic propellant.
发动机使用全流量分级燃烧循环
The engine utilizes the full flow stage combustion cycle,
两种推进剂全部流经预燃室
which means both propellants flow through a preburner,
推动各自的涡轮 带动各自的泵
which then powers turbines, which then spin the pumps.
这可以让推进剂释放出最大可能的功率
This has the potential to unleash the absolute maximum amount of power possible from the propellant,
也可以让预燃室以超低的温度运转
or it could be tuned to actually operate at lower temperatures inside the preburners
或者以上两者的折中
or some happy compromise of both.
SpaceX是世界上"唯三"尝试制造这种循环类型发动机的组织
SpaceX is only the third entity to attempt to build and manufacture this type of engine
曾有苏联在六十年代制造的RD-270发动机
proceeded by the Soviets who built the RD-270 in the 60s
和航空喷气洛克达因公司在90年代研发的"集成动力头"
and Aerojet and Rocketdyne who developed just the power pack of a full flow engine
它只是全流量发动机的半系统
called the integrated power head demonstrator in the 90s.
猛禽发动机由多种金属材料制造
Raptor is made out of many different metals,
Inconel alloys "因科耐尔合金"
耐氧化、耐腐蚀 适用于高温高压的严苛环境的合金
从因科耐尔合金到我们了解不多的SpaceX自家的SX500合金
from inconel alloys to SpaceX's own SX500 alloy that we don't know a ton about,
铜 铝 不锈钢 各种不同的合金
two copper aluminum and steel alloys, just kind of lots of different stuff.
据我们所知 猛禽一二代之间材料的变化并不多
As far as we know, the materials haven't changed all that much between Raptor 1 and 2,
不过他们的确为了提高性能与耐用性而不断调整具体的配方
although they're constantly tweaking the exact formulas for high performance and durability,
发动机的某些部件是3D打印制造的
some parts of the engine are 3D printed,
有些是便于制造原型机 有些部件则会继续使用3D打印量产
which is great for prototyping and likely some parts will continue to be 3D printed, always.
不过随着产量的提升
Although as production continues to ramp up,
SpaceX开始慢慢淘汰3D打印件 加快生产 降低成本
they're starting to get rid of some of those 3D printed parts for quicker and potentially cheaper manufacturing.
猛禽发动机的摆动范围非常大
Raptor has an incredible gimbling range.
许多火箭通过在两个轴向摆动发动机来让火箭转向
Most rockets steer by swiveling the engines on two axis' in order to point and guide the rocket,
推力矢量
称为发动机摆动
which is known as gimbling.
猛禽发动机可以在Z和Y轴上摆动正负15度
Raptor has the ability to swing 15 degrees on the Z and the Y axis.
这个范围相当的大
This is a pretty extreme amount of gimbaling.
可能是所有火箭的主发动机里范围最大的
I think it's actually the most of any main propulsive engine.
比如 SpaceX自家的猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰火箭
For example, SpaceX's Merlin engine could swivel up to five degrees
一级中央的梅林发动机最大可以摆动正负5度
on the center Merlin engine of the first stage of their Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavies.
航天飞机和太空发射系统(SLS)的RS-25发动机可以摆动正负25度
The Space Shuttle and SLS' RS-25 can gimble up to 12.5 degrees
因为RS-25要持续抵抗外挂燃料箱和固推燃烧 分离导致的火箭重心变化
and they had to do so to continually send the power through the constantly changing center of mass
as the side mounted external fuel tank and solid rocket boosters drain propellant and when they were jettisoned.
所以 15度范围真的很大
So 15 degrees is a lot,
它不但范围大 为了应对发动机熄火 摆动的速度还快
and not only can it move far, it can do so very quickly in order to handle engine out capabilities.
SpaceX在星舰高空试飞中有意无意地测试过这一点
SpaceX practiced this intentionally and not on their Starship high altitude test flights
他们让火箭以尽可能低的加速度爬升到10公里高空
as a way to continually keep acceleration as low as possible on the climb to 10 kilometers,
在某台发动机达到最低节流限度时关闭一台
they would shut down engines once the engines reached their lowest throttle point.
当一台发动机关机时 它会迅速"躲开"
When an engine shut down, it quickly moved out of the way,
第一台发动机关机
其他正常运行的发动机会迅速调整方向 接管火箭的控制
and the other engines needed to gimbal quickly to catch the rocket and maintain control.
第二台发动机关机
这些极端状况决定了发动机摆动作动器的摆动行程与总扭矩需求
These extreme cases are what drive the gimbal limits
and overall torque requirements of the actuators that steer the engines.
猛禽发动机从第一台下线以来就在不断进化
Raptor has been continually evolving since the very first one off the line,
不过在猛禽2大幅修改设计之前
but even before the major redesign of Raptor 2,
我们已经看到过一些猛禽1的简化版本 有时称其为"猛禽1.5"
we saw some simplified Raptor 1 versions sometimes called Raptor version 1.5,
这些发动机首次安装在SN15上
that first flew on SN15,
之后还安装在了超重助推4和星舰20上
and it was also the kind of engines that they installed on Super Heavy Booster 4 and Ship 20.
这些发动机最显眼的是它们的绿色钟形喷管
These engines stood out with their green engine bells,
现在大家已经习惯了这样的颜色
which we've now grown accustomed to as it's become the norm.
它们来自于新材料与新的制造工艺
This is caused by new materials and a new manufacturing process.
2022年初 猛禽2发动机首次公开亮相
At the beginning of 2022, we saw the first Raptor 2 publicly,
标志着猛禽1时代的终结
which marked the end of Raptor 1.
猛禽2将用于所有新火箭上
Raptor 2 is utilized on any new vehicle,
2022年7月14日
但在视频发布时 猛禽2还未执行过飞行任务
but as of the making of this video, Raptor 2 hasn't flown yet,
它的首飞将是星舰的首次轨道测试飞行
but it will debut flying on the first orbital test of Starship.
我们来看看如何区分猛禽1和猛禽2
So let's go over how to spot the differences between Raptor 1 and Raptor 2.
并介绍两者的部分参数
And talk about some of the specifics between each one.
区别
肉眼区分猛禽1和猛禽2其实非常简单
Spotting the differences between Raptor 1 and Raptor 2 is actually really easy.
首先 相比猛禽1发动机 猛禽2就像未完工一样
First off, in comparison to Raptor 1, Raptor 2 looks like it's basically not finished.
猛禽2没有了1代上盘丝洞一样的线缆管路
It's missing that rat's nest of wires, adoring all sides of the engine that was very obvious on Raptor 1.
这些线缆对于发动机的研发是必要的
All of these additional wires were necessary during the development of the engine.
每个线缆或管路都连接着压力或温度之类的传感器
Each wire or tube was hooked up to some kind of sensor like a pressure or temperature sensor,
帮助团队调整并控制这台极其复杂的火箭发动机
which helped the teams tune and tame this extremely complicated engine.
因此总体而言 猛禽2发动机看上去非常非常简洁
So in general, Raptor 2 looks much, much cleaner.
一些阀门也被整合进了几个小控制盒内
Some of the valve work has actually been unified into a few small boxes too.
马斯克的"最好的部件是没有部件"的理念在这里得到了充分展现
You can tell Elon's mantra of "the best part is no part" is being played out heavily.
移除大量的线缆与敏感部件后
By stripping down wires and sensitive components,
整台发动机也会更加防火 耐高温
it also makes the engines more flame and heatproof.
SpaceX正在试图优化掉整个发动机隔热罩 从而为发动机减重
SpaceX is attempting to remove heat shielding shrouds entirely
发动机隔热罩
SpaceX正在试图优化掉整个发动机隔热罩 从而为发动机减重
to lighten up the engine and to simplify them.
SpaceX还要尽可能移除发动机的点火器
SpaceX has also gone about removing engine igniters where possible.
通常 燃料和氧化剂在接触的时候
Usually when your fuel and oxidizer come in contact with each other,
仍然需要点火源来保证稳定顺畅的初始燃烧
they still need a source of ignition to ensure stable and smooth initial combustion.
SpaceX曾在主燃烧室和两个预燃室内使用火炬点火器
SpaceX used what are known as torch igniters inside the preburners and inside the main combustion chamber.
通过简化设计 他们成功提高了预燃室内火炬点火器的可靠性
SpaceX was able to simplify and presumably make the torch igniters in the preburners more reliable,
而马斯克提到 他们甚至能够移除主燃烧室内的火炬点火器
but Elon mentioned, they were able to remove torch igniters from the main combustion chamber.
因为进入主燃烧室的燃料和氧化剂已经是极高温度的燃气
This would be possible since the fuel and oxidizer come into the main combustion chamber
as extremely hot gases.
"气-气"反应使推进剂在合适条件下能干净且充分地混合并燃烧
Having a gas-gas interaction allows for a clean and well mixed interactions of propellant
that will happily combust under the right conditions.
然而这需要极其精确和准确的发动机时序控制
It does however require extremely precise and accurate timing.
因此 相比梅林发动机 猛禽发动机的启动程序极其复杂
So the start sequence for Raptor is insanely complicated compared to the start sequence for Merlin.
一切都要完美精准控制 因为互相之间都有依赖——
It has to be perfectly precise cause each one relies -
这一切就好像是在燃料和液氧动力头之间的刀尖上跳舞一样
Basically you're doing this, this delicate dance
between the fuel power head and the oxygen power head,
两者一旦同步出问题
and if they get out of sync,
正常是极度富氧/富燃状态的
预燃室可能就跑到理想燃烧比 直接被烧穿或炸烂了
then you can go stoiciometric in the preburners and melt or explode the preburners.
但是被优化掉的不仅有线缆 点火器 隔热罩
But wires, igniters and shrouds aren't the only things being taken off.
有些发动机还缺少摆动机构等关键部件
Some of the engines are missing some vital parts entirely such as the gimbles.
猛禽2在初期会推出几个版本 未来可能还会更多
Raptor 2 will come in a few variants at first and perhaps more later on.
比如超重助推最外圈的发动机不会安装摆动机构
There will be engines that lack steering gimbles such as the engines fitted to the outer ring of the booster.
固定发动机
摆动发动机
外圈一共有20台发动机 它们并不需要有摆动能力
There's going to be 20 engines on the outer perimeter and they actually don't require gimbles.
火箭的转向控制可以通过中圈内圈的13台发动机实现
Steering authority can be accomplished by these center engines
或者通过推力差 调节火箭两侧发动机的推力来完成
or perhaps with some thrust differential, or throttling the engines on one side of the rocket or the other.
星舰上面的真空猛禽发动机也将是无摆动的版本
There's also going to be the vacuum Raptor engines on Starship, which are fixed as well.
移除摆动能力意味着减去了摆动作动器和万向节支架自身的重量
Removing the ability to gimble also means they can remove the heavy actuators
along with the actual gimble mount itself.
法兰
大家还会注意到 发动机上一些法兰也不见了
Next you'll notice some flanges have been removed
焊接
因为SpaceX想要通过焊接尽可能消除管路的连接件
as SpaceX works on either welding as many connections as they can, or just deleting them if possible.
而随着设计的日益成熟
But as the design gets more and more mature,
很多部件的探查与维护需求会越来越少
serviceability and access to everything isn't nearly as necessary,
移除这些法兰后 也会让发动机更加可靠 重量也更轻
and by removing flanges, it can actually make the whole engine more reliable and lighter weight as well.
最后 猛禽2最大的基础性修改可能是喷管喉部略微扩大
Lastly, perhaps one of the biggest fundamental changes to Raptor 2
was the decision to open up the throat a little bit.
喉部越宽 让更多的推进剂流经系统的潜力就更大
The wider the throat, the more potential there is to flow more propellant through the system.
膨胀比=喷管出口面积/喷管喉部面积
然而 这种设计实际上会降低膨胀比
But it actually reduces the efficiency by reducing the expansion ratio,
——即喷嘴出口面积与喉部面积之比 从而降低发动机的效率
or the ratio between the area of the nozzle exit and the area of the throat.
喷管出口
喷管喉部
更高的膨胀比可以让喷管更有效地把压力转换为速度
The higher the expansion ratio, the more work the nozzle does to convert high pressure into high velocity.
高压
高速
因此总体来说 工程师更希望有尽可能高的膨胀比
Generally, engineers want as high of an expansion ratio as possible,
尤其对于真空中运行的发动机来说
especially when operating in the vacuum of space,
但海平面发动机的设计又会受到外界环境大气压力的限制
but they're often limited to ambient air pressure considerations for sea level engines.
av841875408
感谢@长五遥三没有鸽
如果上面哪句话让你很困惑 欢迎观看我介绍气尖发动机的视频
If all of what I just said is kind of confusing, maybe watch my video on Aerospike engines.
那个视频中详细讨论了膨胀比 气流分离以及效率等话题
We talk a lot about expansion ratios, flow separation, and efficiency in that video.
在未来 我一定会制作一期更新的视频 专门深入探讨这个主题
In the future, I'll definitely do an updated video all about this topic in general.
不过这次喷管喉部的设计改进可能会提升发动机的推力
But this opening of the throat has the potential to increase the thrust of the engine
尽管略微降低了效率
despite its slight decrease in efficiency.
因此 我认为现在是时候实际比较一下猛禽2和猛禽1的参数
So I think it's time we actually compare the specs of Raptor 2 versus Raptor 2,
看看这些微小的修改带来了哪些影响
to see what effect all these little changes have made.
参数对比
将猛禽1和猛禽2放在一起对比
Seeing Raptor 1 and Raptor 2 side by side,
可以发现它们尺寸几乎相同
we can see they're basically the same dimensions.
虽然大小差不多 但它们并不兼容
And although they're the same dimensions, they are not compatible,
使用猛禽2的火箭无法安装猛禽1 反之亦然
you would not be able to use a Raptor 1 engine on a vehicle that uses Raptor 2 and vice versa,
虽然这种情况并不会发生
although that would never happen.
每台发动机高度约3米 喷口直径约1.3米
Each engine stands about three meters tall and is about 1.3 meters wide at the nozzle exit.
整体来看它其实是款非常小巧的发动机
And they're actually pretty small engines in the grand scheme of things.
相比于航天飞机和SLS芯级的RS-25发动机来说
Compared to the RS-25 that powered the Space Shuttle and is what powers the core stage of the SLS rocket,
猛禽发动机体积更小 推力更大
Raptor is much smaller and more powerful.
而且猛禽发动机重量非常轻
And Raptor is extremely light.
我们并不清楚两款发动机的准确重量
Now we don't know the exact mass for either engine,
相比之下
RS-25重量是3吨多
只知道猛禽1大约是2吨
but we do know Raptor 1 was right around 2000 kilograms,
马斯克说猛禽2会轻20% 那就是大约1.6吨
and Elon said, Raptor 2 is about 20% lighter, so around 1600 kilograms.
接下来是两者的推力 猛禽1海平面推力约185吨
Next, their thrust, Raptor 1 was operating at about 185 tons of thrust,
刚好和RS-25的海平面推力几乎相同
which just so happens to be almost the exact same amount of thrust as the RS-25
而猛禽2的海平面推力已经达到了230吨
and Raptor 2 is already operating at 230 tons of thrust.
这部分推力的提升主要来自猛禽2燃烧室室压的提升
This increase in thrust comes mostly from the increased chamber pressure of Raptor 2.
猛禽1运行时的燃烧室室压是250bar
Raptor 1 was operating at about 250 bar,
这个压力已经是火箭发动机中相当高的了
which to be clear was already about the highest operating pressure of almost any engine,
但这还只是开始
but that's still just the beginning.
猛禽2目前运行时燃烧室室压是300bar 并且他们认为还能进一步提高
Raptor 2 is currently operating at 300 bar and they think they can get quite a bit higher yet.
这个数值极其震撼
That is absolutely an astonishing number.
之前保持的纪录是俄罗斯的RD-180发动机 267bar
The Russian RD-180 was the previous record holder at 267 bar,
所以猛禽发动机的确打破了这一纪录
so Raptor is really breaking some records here.
燃烧室室压的提升 加上猛禽2喉部面积略有增加
This increase in chamber pressure, along with Raptor 2 having a slightly wider throat area,
导致我们看到的推力的增加
has led to that increase in thrust that we see.
但喷管喉部设计的改动与膜冷却流量的增加也稍稍降低了猛禽2的整体效率
But changes to the throat and an increase in film cooling has slightly decreased the overall efficiency of Raptor 2.
猛禽1的海平面比冲是330秒
Raptor 1 hit about 330 seconds of specific impulse at sea level,
猛禽2会少一点点 比冲大约是327秒
while Raptor 2 is just a few seconds less, likely around 327 seconds of specific impulse.
纸面数值上 这的确是一个退步
Now that might seem like a step backwards, and on paper, it is.
但反直觉的是 把这些数值代入火箭的一级上
But believe it or not, if we run the numbers on how this affects the first stage,
我们会发现起飞时全箭更高的推重比实际比更高的比冲更有用
we'll see that having a higher thrust-to-weight ratio of the overall stage
actually gets more work done than having a higher specific impulse.
原因来自于所谓的"重力损失"
This is due to something called gravity loss or gravity drag.
地球引力会以一倍重力加速度时刻向下拉拽物体
Since gravity pulls at everything here on earth with one G of force,
因此在发射初期 火箭必须克服这 9.8 m/s² 的重力加速度
gravity is going to be eating up that first 9.8 m/s² of acceleration.
因此 只有火箭推重比大于1:1
So until you produce more than a 1:1 thrust-to-weight ratio,
即火箭推力大于自身重量
or until your rocket is making more thrust than it weighs,
它才能飞起来
it will literally go nowhere.
而一旦推重比超过1:1 火箭能做的功将会有显著提升
And then there are massive increases in the amount of work done
when your thrust weight ratio gets above 1:1.
如果我们的推重比是1:1 那么全部的推力都要用来抵抗重力
If our thrust weight ratio is 1:1, 100% of our thrust is spent fighting gravity,
0%的推力用来送我们上天
and 0% of our thrust can get us somewhere.
所以净加速度是0
And as you know, that means our net acceleration is zero.
如果推重比来到1.25:1
If our thrust-to-weight ratio is 1.25:1,
那么其中80%的推力会用来抵抗重力
80% of our thrust is still spent fighting gravity,
只有20%的推力用于起飞 起飞净加速度是0.25G
and only 20% is used getting us somewhere with a net acceleration of 0.25 Gs.
相比起飞推重比1:1来说 已经提升相当多了
But this produces infinitely more work than a thrust-to-weight ratio of 1:1
毕竟前者根本飞不起来
since that wasn't producing any.
假如起飞推重比提升到1.5:1
So let's jump up to a thrust-to-weight ratio of 1.5:1.
那么67%的推力浪费在抵抗重力上 33%的推力用来加速火箭
Now 67% of our thrust is wasted to gravity and 33% goes into accelerating the vehicle.
此时相比1.25:1的推重比 我们推力只提升了20%
So although we only increased our thrust 20% over a thrust-to-weight ratio of 1.25:1,
但做的功却翻倍了
we actually produced twice as much work,
起飞净加速度来到了0.5G
giving us a net acceleration of 0.5 Gs.
而这就是猛禽1到猛禽2大致的提升量
And that's approximately the thrust increase from Raptor 1 to Raptor 2.
实际数值 猛禽2的推力提升约24%
Actually, Raptor 2 has about a 24% increase in thrust.
所以在一级满燃料点火时 它们能做两倍的功
So they can actually get over double the amount of work done
at the beginning of the first stage burn when it's full of fuel.
显然 完成两倍的功远比提高一两个百分点的效率要好得多
Obviously getting twice as much work done is much better than a percent or two more efficient.
那么这就是猛禽1和猛禽2的直接对比
Okay, that's the direct comparison of Raptor 1 versus Raptor 2,
但这可是SpaceX啊
but this is SpaceX.
他们肯定不会就此停止压榨发动机性能
We know they aren't done pushing this thing,
马斯克已经提到目前仍在推动的多项改进
and Elon already has mentioned many improvements they're currently working on,
因此让我们用对未来的展望 为本期视频做个结尾
so let's wrap this up with what changes we can expect to see in the future.
猛禽的未来
首先 我认为SpaceX会继续努力让猛禽发动机更适合低成本批量生产
First off, I think the number one thing we're going to see
is SpaceX continue to try to make Raptor more and more production friendly and cheaper.
马斯克非常痴迷于降低每台发动机的制造成本
Elon is obsessed with reducing the cost per unit,
我知道制造价格对于完全可复用的火箭似乎并不那么重要
but I know price doesn't really seem all that important when the rocket is fully reusable
因为火箭可以反复多次使用
because they can just reuse it over and over.
但SpaceX想得更远
But SpaceX is dreaming big
他们设想未来这些航天器会像今天的客机一样习以为常
and pictures these vehicles being about as common in the future as airliners are today.
为了简化发动机设计 SpaceX还在尝试移除喉部的膜冷却
In an attempt to simplify the engine, SpaceX is also attempting to remove throat film cooling.
膜冷却
av723951018
看过《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》的观众应该记得
As those of you who watched my "Why don't rocket engines melt" video might know,
把少量燃料直接注入发动机喷管喉部可以辅助冷却
it's common to inject extra fuel directly into the throat of the engine to help cool it.
在其他地方进行更保守的设计就有可能实现移除喉部膜冷却
Removing throat film cooling can be accomplished by being more conservative in other areas,
膜冷却
比如增加头部 也就是喷注器的膜冷却
such as increasing the head in film cooling, otherwise known as injector film cooling,
或者干脆让主燃烧室内进行更加富燃的燃烧
or even just going further fuel rich in your overall main combustion chamber.
SpaceX目前正在研究并评估这样的简化设计是否值得
SpaceX is currently studying and evaluating whether or not it's worth it to simplify the engine,
虽然扩大头部的膜冷却规模会导致性能的损失
despite the performance hit, it will take from additional head in film cooling.
但考虑到他们对简化设计的追求 我们未来或许能看到该技术的实现
But with the obsession to simplify the engine, perhaps this will be something we see in the future.
另一方面 预计猛禽发动机的燃烧室室压和推力将进一步提升
Another thing to look for, we definitely expect to see Raptor increase chamber pressure and thrust.
我们已知他们的推力目标是250吨
We know they're aiming to reach about 250 tons of thrust,
意味着主燃烧室室压会逼近330bar
which would likely be closer to 330 bar in the main chamber.
SpaceX已经在之前的测试中达到过330bar
SpaceX has hit 330 bar in a test before,
但要实现稳定运行仍需进一步改进
but sustaining that will take additional improvements.
不过还是要记住 猛禽发动机仍处于开发的初级阶段
One of the biggest things to remember is overall Raptor is still very much in its infancy.
马斯克提到过 梅林发动机已经进化到其初始版本的两倍以上性能
Elon has mentioned how the Merlin engine has been evolved to be over twice as powerful as when it first came out,
梅林现在几乎被榨干了全部潜力
but that engine has pretty much reached its full potential.
而此时 猛禽才刚刚起步
So in this case, Raptor is still just at the very beginning.
我期待着猛禽未来推力更大 重量更轻 更可靠 成本更低
I expect it to continue to become more powerful, lighter, more reliable, and cheaper,
我相信很快就能看到 我相信SpaceX有能力做到
and I expect it to do all of these things in a hurry, now that SpaceX has the means to do so.
大家怎么看呢?
So what do you think?
大家认为猛禽2相比猛禽1 改进算巨大吗?
Do you think Raptor 2 is a nice big improvement over Raptor 1?
还是你觉得这仅仅是开始?
Or do you kind of think this is just the beginning?
或者说猛禽路线根本走不通?
Or maybe you think Raptor is a dead end
未来某天SpaceX会回到梅林这样更简单的发动机上?
and we'll actually see SpaceX go back to a simpler engine, more like Merlin or something someday.
欢迎在评论区分享你的想法
Let me know your thoughts and the comments below.
大家可能注意到了视频中猛禽1和猛禽2的精致建模
I'm sure you noticed the incredible Raptor 1 and Raptor 2 renderings in this video,
感谢@Caspar_Stanley和@IzanRamos2002两位
those were thanks to Izan Ramos and Casper Stanley
他们是技艺精湛 非常优秀的3D艺术家
who are just some of the most incredibly talented 3D artists out there.
感谢所有Patreon上的赞助者
让本期视频成为可能
And I also owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters
for helping make videos like this
让《天天太空人》这个节目中的一切成为可能
and everything else we do here at Everyday Astronaut possible.
如果你想赞助我们
想加入Discord频道 想提前观看视频
If you wanna show your support
and gain access to our Discord channel or early access to videos,
欢迎前往下方链接进行赞助
head it over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
网上冲浪的时候也可以看看网店里这些酷炫的新品
And while you're online, be sure and check out all the incredible new things we have up in our web store,
比如我这件衬衫
such as these dress wear shirts.
还有其他的图案 比如格栅舵 龙飞船 登月器等等
And we've got other cool patterns too, including grid fins, dragon capsules, and lunar landers.
还有"太空军校生"栏目下的新的童装周边产品
But also lots of other really cool stuff like some new merch for tiny humans under our "Space Cadet" section,
印着"正常"的袜子 1:100的猎鹰九号火箭模型
some nominal socks, or our 1:100 scale Falcon 9 model rockets,
不过暂时还没货
well at least when they get back in stock.
总之各种有趣商品 都在下方链接中
Find it all at everydayastronaut.com slash shop.
感谢大家 就到这里了 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Thanks everybody. That's gonna do it for me. I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
把航天知识带给寻常百姓家~
bringing space down to earth for everyday people.